So today's דף ל"ב *Daf Lamed Bet* we pick up at the
bottom of ל"א עמוד ב' *Lamed Aleph Amud Bet*
and we are discussing the nine תקנות takkanot *takkanot* of רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai*. We mentioned
eight: five in this פרק perek *perek*, one in the previous פרק
*perek*, a lot of them having to do with the transition away
from the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*,
and one about a גר *ger* who converts nowadays should not set
aside the money for the קרבן *korban*, also a transition away from
the מקדש *Mikdash*.
That gets us up
to, sorry, six in this פרק *perek*, one in the previous makes
seven, then the גר *ger* makes us eight, and the ninth one
is now an issue of debate. So let's take a look. לאידך
*L'idach*, the ninth one, פלוגתא דרב פפא ורב נחמן בר יצחק *plugta
d'Rav Pappa v'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*. רב פפא Rav Pappa? *Rav Pappa*
says כרם רבעי kerem reva'i *Kerem Reva'i*. It's the issue about the
כרם רבעי Kerem Revai, *Kerem Reva'i* about the fruit from the vineyard
in the fourth year. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
*Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* says
לשון של זהורית *lashon shel zehorit*, it's about the red string. רב
פפא Rav Pappa *Rav Pappa* said כרם רבעי *Kerem Reva'i*, as we
taught in a משנה Mishnah *Mishna*: כרם רבעי היה עולה לירושלים מהלך
יום לכל צד *Kerem
Reva'i haya oleh l'Yerushalayim mahalach yom l'chol tzad*. That if you have,
you know, the fruit or the, here it's the fruit of the
vine, there's a question whether it's all fruit or specifically grapes grown
in the fourth year, then you bring them to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*
and you eat them there. But of course if you don't want
to שלעפ *schlep*, you can convert it to money, you can redeem
it on money and bring the money to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. You can
technically do that even if you're just one foot outside of ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*, but the Rabbis made a תקנה takkanah *takkana* that if you're
within a day's travel, you are not allowed to redeem and bring
the money. We want you to be bringing the fruit itself because
part of the whole idea is we want ירושלים *Yerushalayim* to be
filled with all this new fruit. So a day's journey on any
side of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, you would have to bring it to ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*. וזו היא תחומה *v'zu hi tchuma*, and this is the boundaries,
this is the cities that are a day away from ירושלים *Yerushalayim*:
אילת מן הצפון *Eilat min hatzafon*, now it can't really be אילת
*Eilat* because אילת *Eilat* is a lot more than one day away
from ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So anyway, there's a question here, is it in
the north or is it in the south, but it's a different
אילת *Eilat*. עקרבת מן הדרום *Akravat min hadarom*, let's say, and עקרבת
*Akravat* in the south. לוד
מן המערב *Lud min hama'arav*, Lud is in the
west of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. To me it would seem that would be
more than a day, I don't know how fast horses go. וירדן
מן המזרח *v'Yarden min hamizrach*, and the Jordan to the east. Okay,
so if you're within
that, you have to bring it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. ואמר עולא *v'amar
Ulla*, Ulla said, ואיכא דאמרי רבה בר בר עולא *v'ika d'amri Rabba
bar bar Ulla*, אמר רבי amar Rabbi יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, מה
טעם *ma ta'am*, what's the reason? כדי לעטר שוקי ירושלים בפירות *k'dei
l'ateir shukei Yerushalayim b'peirot*, in order that the marketplaces of Jerusalem should
be adorned with fruit whenever anybody is bringing the fruit and not
just bringing money. ותנן v'tnan בברייתא *v'tnan b'Braita*, we taught in a
ברייתא Baraita *Braita*, כרם רבעי היה לו לרבי אליעזר במזרח לוד *Kerem
Reva'i haya lo l'Rabbi Eliezer bemizrach Lud*. That Rabbi Eliezer had כרם
רבעי *Kerem Reva'i* to the east of Lud, so to the east
of Lud is in the direction of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so he would
have to bring the fruit itself. בצד כפר טבי *b'tzad Kfar Tavi*,
by the village of Kfar Tavi. וביקש רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer להפקיר
לעניים *v'bikeish Rabbi Eliezer l'hifkir l'aniyim*. He didn't want to have to
שלעפ *schlep* it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so he went ahead and he
was about to make it הפקיר *hefkir* to the poor, let the
poor take it and take it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, I'd rather they
take it than I would have to שלעפ *schlep* it. אמרו לו
תלמידיו *amru lo talmidav*, his students said to him, רבי Rebbi, *Rebbi*,
master, כבר נמנו חבריך עליו והתירוהו *kvar nimnu chaveirecha alav v'hitiruhu*. Your
colleagues already took a vote and made it permissible, they annulled that
תקנה takkanah *takkana*. Now, מאן חבריך *man chaveirecha*, who are your colleagues?
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai*.
That would have been רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai.
*Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai*. So that's what רב פפא *Rav Pappa* claims,
that the colleagues were רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai,
*Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai*. And that was his תקנה takkanah *takkana* post
חורבן *Churban*. You know, post חורבן *Churban* people are not bringing, ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* is destroyed and it's under Roman rule or whatever. The purpose
of this תקנה takkanah *takkana* no longer applies, so again, an acceptance
of the post חורבן *Churban* reality and annulling this תקנה takkanah *takkana*.
There's no need to actually be bringing the fruit itself to ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*. So that is one version, and again, very much of a
similar genre. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak? אמר לשון
של זהורית *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar lashon shel zehorit*. No, it
was something different, it was something actually not post חורבן *Churban*, but
this is one that actually is going to be identified as pre
חורבן *Churban*, related to the קרבנות Korbanos, *korbanot* of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur*, to the שעיר לעזאזל *Seir L'Azazel*. It was the
red string. דתניא *d'tanya*, as we taught in a ברייתא Baraita *Braita*,
בראשונה היו קושרין לשון של זהורית על פתח אולם מבחוץ *barishona hayu
koshrin lashon shel zehorit al petach
ulam mibachutz*. Originally they would tie the red string by the opening
of the אולם *Ulam*, the hallway to the היכל *Heichal* on the
outside. הלבין *hilbin*, if it turned white after the קרבן *korban* was
brought, היו שמחים *hayu smeichim*, everybody would rejoice. לא הלבין *lo hilbin*,
if it would not turn white, היו עצבים *hayu atzeivim*, they would
all be anguished, they would feel that their sins weren't atoned for.
התקינו hitkinu שיהיו קושרין אותו על פתח אולם מבפנים *hitkinu sheyihyu koshrin
oto al petach ulam mibifnim*. So they put it on the inside
of the doorway. ועדיין היו מציצין ורואין *v'adayin hayu matzitzin v'ro'in*, and
they would still peep and see. through and look. הלבין היו שמחים,
לא הלבין היו עצובים and if they would turn white they'd be
happy and if not they'd be sad. התקינו so finally they established
שיהו קושרים אותו חציו בסלע וחציו בין קרניו sheyehu koshrim oto chetzyo
basela v'chetzyo bein karnav
של שעיר המשתלח shel sa'ir hamishtale'ach in a place where the people
wouldn't see it. Half of it would be tied to the rock
right before they threw the goat over and the other between the
horns of the goat itself.
It's interesting because still people wanted to find out, why did you
have to tie it anywhere? You know, why didn't you just leave
it on the horns and nobody will see? So presumably they still
wanted the information, but they didn't necessarily—I don't know, they wanted to
control the information, they didn't want it to get out if it
was bad news. רב נחמן בר יצחק so anyway and he's assuming
that this final תקנה takkanah, was that of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי.
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. So that would be an actual תקנה takkanah
of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. during the period
of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So let's take a look. רב
נחמן בר יצחק מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב פפא? Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rav Pappa? Why didn't he say like
רב פפא? Which is the issue about the כרם רבעי which fits
very nicely in the whole theme of the תקנות takkanot of רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. אמר
לך amar lach he'll tell you אי סלקא דעתך רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי ei salka deitach Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai if you're saying that
those that annulled that תקנה takkanah of bringing the fruit to ירושלים
without redeeming it is רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
so חבירך דרבי אליעזר מי הוי? chaveirach d'Rabbi Eliezer mi hava? They
wouldn't have said to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, "your colleagues." He wasn't
a colleague of רבי Rebbi אליעזר, רבו הוה, rabo hava, he was
a rebbi, he was an earlier generation. ואידך v'idach so that's a
good point, so what's the response back? No. כיון דתלמידים הוו keivan
d'talmidim havu since it was רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's students that were
telling him that the גזרה gezeirah was annulled, so לאו אורח ארעא
למימר להו לרבי רבך lav orech ar'a l'meimar lehu l'rabbi rabach or
רבך. rabacha. It would be inappropriate for the students to say to
their master "but your rebbi annulled it," right? So it's sort of
like, you know, bringing their master down, you know, somebody who's a
bigger authority than you annulled it. So as a way of respect
they said "your colleagues" annulled it, but really it was רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai All right, that's a pretty reasonable
explanation. So now let's look at the other idea that it was
the red string. ורב פפא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב נחמן בר
יצחק? v'Rav Pappa mai ta'ama lo amar k'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak? Why
does רב פפא not say like רב נחמן בר יצחק? So for
me before you get to reasons why it's hard, you know, why
it doesn't make sense to say it at all, I would just
say that this תקנה does not seem at all to fit in
the genre of the תקנות takkanot of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai It's pre-חורבן המקדש, Churban HaMikdash, it doesn't really, you
know, there's nothing that really would make it want you to associate
this thing with the red string with רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai But the גמרא Gemara actually gives even a more
concrete reason why it's—why it's very difficult to make that claim. Let's
take a look. אמר לך amar lach he'll tell
you אי סלקא דעתך רבן יוחנן בן זכאי ei salka deitach Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai if it was רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai who did the thing with the red string, בימי רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי מי הוו לשון של זהורית מלבין? bimei Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai mi havu lashon shel zehorit malbin? Since when was there
a red string in his days? והתניא v'hatanya it was taught in
a ברייתא beraisa. כל שנותיו של רבן יוחנן בן זכאי מאה ועשרים
שנה. kol shnotav shel Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai me'ah v'esrim shanah. So
apparently רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. lived 120 years.
ארבעים שנה עסק בפרקמטיא arba'im shanah asak b'prakmatya the first 40 years
he devoted to business. So he made himself a good פרנסה parnassah
so he could put the money in the bank and then devote
the next 80 years to learning and leadership. ארבעים שנה למד arba'im
shanah lamad 40 years he learned תורה Torah and ארבעים שנה לימד
arba'im shanah limad 40 years he taught תורה. Torah. Okay, and we're
going to assume obviously that any of his edicts, you know, any
of his positions of authority is going to be only once he
started teaching, not when he was still in the role of a
student. ותניא v'tanya it was taught in a ברייתא beraisa, ארבעים שנה
קודם שנחרב הבית לא היה לשון של זהורית מלבין. arba'im shanah kodem
shenechrav habayit lo hayah lashon shel zehorit malbin. So the string did
not turn white for the 40 years leading up to the חורבן
הבית. Churban HaBayit. אלא מאדים ela madim it stayed red. Okay, ותנן
and we taught in the משנה Mishnah, משחרב הבית התקין רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי mishcharav habayit hitkin Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai that רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai we know made תקנות takanot after
the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayit. So meaning what does that tell you?
It tells you the following. If here
you have חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayit,
okay, is at this point here. Okay, and here we know that
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי was doing his thing after חורבן הבית. Churban
HaBayit. So that means for 40 years he was teaching, right? So
that goes for 40 years back. So let's just say this was
year one. Okay, so this is year 39
BCH, before חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayit, okay.
All
right, so his role as being a—teaching was for 40 years, so
at most it got back to year 39 before חורבן הבית, Churban
HaBayit, right? But 40 years before חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayit, year 40
BCH, right, it was no longer turning white. Why? No longer turning
white. And since the תקנה speaks about the fact that it sometimes
would turn white and sometimes turn
red, right, that was the whole point of the תקנה, clearly the
תקנה was made sometime back here. But רבן יוחנן בן זכאי only
started his leadership role at most 39 years beforehand, after it no
longer was turning white and the תקנה was made while it was
still sometimes turning white. Okay, so clearly this could not have been
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי'ס Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai's activity, his activity was
all here. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אוקיי, okay, ואידך v'idach the response back would be אותם ארבעים
שנה דלמד otam arba'im shanah d'lamad those 40 years that he learned...
years when he was learning even before he started teaching, תלמיד יושב
לפני רבו הוה. Talmid yoshev lifnei rabo hava. He was not just
סתם stam learning on his own, he was there in the presence
of his רבי, Rebbi and he was like you know involved in
the types of you know activities that his רבי Rebbi was involved
in. ואמר מילתא Va'amar milta and while he was sitting in front
of his רבי Rebbi, even though he was a student, he suggested
something. ואסתבר טעמיה, V'istaber tameih, they you know that's a good idea,
we should actually change what we're doing with that red string. וקראו
רבו משמיה, V'karu rabo mishmeih, they attributed it to him. So it's
sort of like when you're a professor and you get your graduate
student to basically write all of your papers for you and then
you get to put your name on it. So here the רבי
didn't put his name on it. He actually put the graduate student's
name on it. So אי הכי נמי Ei hachi nami they did
do it even as a even before his primary years of leadership.
But again, it's a hard it's hard to attribute this to him,
it really has nothing to do with the normal types of תקנות
that we associate with רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Yes?
So the one for the כרם רבעי, there were actually two decrees.
Yes, and the second one basically overturned the first one.
The first decree was that you couldn't redeem it, you had to
bring it. And then what רבן יוחנן בן זכאי did was that
he annulled that first decree. Right, that's correct, just like before, the
decree of not accepting witnesses and then annulling that decree. Right, so
sometimes what he decreed was to annul a previous decree, particularly a
previous decree that was מקדש related. Yes.
Do you think there's associating with משה Moshe the 120 years and
also the
משהלה Moshe'leh 80 when he was 80?
Yeah, so you're an excellent point, you're absolutely yeah you're I mean
obviously the 120 immediately suggests משה. Moshe. I hadn't stopped to think,
but you're absolutely correct, that was משה Moshe as well. Right,
משה's Moshe leadership was his last 40 years. Right, and maybe you
could say that the earlier 40 years, I mean you don't know
in the תורה, Torah, but you could sort of see that as
the education of משה Moshe while he was growing and developing. It's
an yeah.
He taught תורה Torah when he was he
started teaching in the last 40 years. Right, you know it's an
excellent point. I mean it's actually if you think about it that
way, then it's really even like radical, because then it says, well
חורבן הבית Churban haBayis is parallel to leaving מצרים. Mitzrayim.
You know, it's I don't know if חז"ל Chazal were intending that,
but the point still is, you know, one was a good thing,
one was a bad thing obviously, but the point but the point
still is is that it's like a radical shift in our, you
know, in leadership, a radical shift in our religious and you know
national reality and the type of leadership that it requires in order
to guide us, you know, through that period. So I think that
that's yeah, that is an excellent point. Okay, so now we pick
up top of ל"א ע"א Lamed Aleph Amud Aleph to the משנה,
mishna back to things specific to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, we discussed
the שופר, Shofar, now we are going to move to the liturgy.
Let's take a look. סדר ברכות, Seder Brachos, the way you do
the ברכות. Brachos. Now, the assumption here is we are talking about
מוסף Musaf where because we're going to talk about מלכויות, זכרונות ושופרות,
Malchuyos, Zichronos, v'Shofros, so I should mention at the beginning that the
בעל המאור Ba'al HaMaor understands that you would say מלכויות, זכרונות ושופרות
Malchuyos, Zichronos, v'Shofros in all of the תפילות Tfillos of שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esrei. So we are not just talking about מוסף Musaf according
to the בעל המאור, Ba'al HaMaor, we're talking about all the תפילות
Tfillos of שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, but the general assumption, certainly the
way we rule, is we're talking about מוסף. Musaf. Okay? And you
add, oh well I have this, and
and this, okay,
and you add מלכויות, זכרונות ושופרות. Malchuyos, Zichronos, v'Shofros. So the question
is where do you add it? Okay, so there's normally, the normal
structure is, right, אבות, Avos, right, גבורות, Gvuros,
right,
what does he have against אבות Avos and מגן
אברהם?
Magen
Avraham? קדושת
השם,
Kedushas Hashem,
right, הא-ל הקדוש ha'E-l haKadosh or
המלך הקדוש haMelech haKadosh
throughout obviously, yes we'll get to that. Okay, then in a normal
שבת Shabbat you have here
קדושת היום, Kedushas HaYom, let's say for מוסף, Musaf, right, מקדש השבת
וישראל והזמנים, Mekadesh haShabbat v'Yisrael v'haZmanim, right, and then you have עבודה,
Avoda, which is רצה Retzei related to the
קרבנות, מודים Modim and
שים שלום. Sim Shalom. Okay, so whatever, that's your normal seven. Now,
if you wanted to put in מלכויות, זכרונות ושופרות, Malchuyos, Zichronos, v'Shofros,
you'd figure out fine, you put them in let's say here after
you do קדושת היום, Kedushas HaYom, maybe before קדושת היום Kedushas HaYom
and you'd have 10. For whatever reason, the גמרא Gemara assumes that
you're only going to have, or everybody assumes you're only going to
have nine
ברכות Brachos total, not a total of 10. Right, this is seven.
So the question is which are not where are you going to
put them and which which one are you going to conflate together?
Right, so one of these has to be inserted together with one
of the three מלכויות, זכרונות ושופרות, Malchuyos, Zichronos, v'Shofros, if you start
with the assumption that you only have nine and not 10. You're
going to have to combine two. So let's take a look. סדר
ברכות, Seder Brachos, the way you do the ברכות, Brachos, אומר אבות
וגבורות וקדושת השם וכולל מלכויות עמהם ואינו תוקע. Omer Avos u'Gvuros u'Kedushas
Hashem v'kolel Malchuyos imahem v'eino sokeia. Okay, so the first opinion is
you say the מלכויות Malchuyos here. Okay, so מלכויות Malchuyos goes with
with קדושת השם. Kedushas Hashem. We'll discuss why. Wait a minute, let's
just get this down. Without תקיעות. tekiot. שופרות ותוקע, Shofrot v'toke'ah, I'm
sorry, זכרונות ותוקע, Zichronot v'toke'ah, שופרות ותוקע, Shofrot v'toke'ah, ואומר עבודה והודאה
וברכת כהנים. v'omer avoda v'hoda'ah u'birkat Kohanim. Right, so this is called
ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, excuse me, get the right terms, ברכת כהנים,
Birkat Kohanim, because you say obviously the ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim there
and that's מודים Modim as well, okay? Anyway, so דברי, divrei, these
are the words of רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
So he says you say מלכויות Malchuyot here, then you say קדושת
היום Kedushat HaYom and in here you insert זכרונות, Zichronot,
זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות. Shofrot. Okay, that's what רבי יוחנן בן נורי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says. And here he says you do the
תוקע, toke'ah, of course it's just one point, anyway, you do a
תקיעה, tekia, it's okay, you do your תקיעה tekia here, here, and
here. That's what רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says.
All right, so that's רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva, said to him רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, oh, thank you very much, said to him רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, אם אינו תוקע למלכויות למה הוא מזכיר im eino
toke'ah l'Malchuyot lama hu mazkir? Look, the whole point, says רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, of saying מלכויות, Malchuyot, זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות Shofrot presumably
is to connect them to the blowing of the שופר. shofar. So
if you're not going to blow the שופר shofar with the מלכויות,
Malchuyot, forget about it. So that's by the way an important point,
thinking about the relationship of מלכויות, Malchuyot, זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות Shofrot
to the blowing of the שופר. shofar. Are they just a part
of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and the שופר shofar is also a
part of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and sometimes they overlap? If you
think about how we do it, you know, the fact is we
say the ברכה bracha and then we do the תקיעות tekiot and
then after we do the תקיעות, tekiot, we actually say, what do
we say after we do the תקיעות tekiot after we do the
ברכה? bracha? תקבל ברחמים וברצון סדר שופרותינו סדר מלכויותינו. tikabel b'rachamim u'v'ratzon
seder shofroteinu, seder malchuyoteinu. There's a sense that the תקיעות tekiot are,
you know, sort of accompanying or helping, you know, bring the prayers
up to God. There's another way of understanding the relationship, not that
the שופר, shofar, not that the blowing is the way of conveying
the prayers, but the opposite, where it is that the מלכויות, Malchuyot,
זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות Shofrot are helping to frame and characterize what
the תקיעות tekiot are all about, give meaning to the תקיעות, tekiot,
to give meaning by the תקיעות tekiot by we say these different
themes and those themes now characterize, become part of what the תקיעות
tekiot are about. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says one way or
the other, תקיעות tekiot and מלכויות Malchuyot and זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות
Shofrot are intertwined. So I don't understand besides the fact that you're
grouping it there, I can't accept that you don't do תקיעה tekiah
with one of them. So rather says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, אלא
אומר אבות וגבורות וקדושת השם וכולל מלכויות עם קדושת היום ותוקע. ela
omer avot u'gevurot u'kdushat Hashem v'kolel Malchuyot im kdushat hayom v'toke'ah. So
says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, you
do not put מלכויות Malchuyot there, you put... let's try to move
this back over here. Okay, so he's got here זכרונות, Zichronot, זכרונות
Zichronot and שופרות. Shofrot. Okay, and
that's where, this is רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri,
they after this is where you're תוקע. toke'ah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says no, what you do is says רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
you say מלכויות Malchuyot here, זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות. Shofrot. So מלכויות
Malchuyot connects with קדושת השם, Kedushat Hashem, okay, and yes, you do
the three תקיעות... tekiot... קדושת היום, Kedushat HaYom, you do the three
תקיעות tekiot here, that they're agreeing that you do the three תקיעות,
tekiot, you know, sort of in the middle, but now the תקיעות
tekiot link to the מלכויות Malchuyot as well. Each of the תקיעות
tekiot links to מלכויות, Malchuyot, זכרונות Zichronot and שופרות. Shofrot. That's what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. ואומר עבודה והודאה וברכת כהנים. v'omer avoda
v'hoda'ah u'birkat Kohanim.
And then you say the three. Now, the גמרא Gemara is going
to describe, discuss the debate, but before the גמרא Gemara discusses the
debate, I just want to say a word about how do we
פסקן? pasken? So I'm saying, well, of course we פסקן pasken like
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We know we say מלכויות Malchuyot in קדושת
היום. Kedushat HaYom. What is the ברכה bracha we say by קדושת,
Kedushat, besides that we actually say the מלכויות Malchuyot by the קדושת
היום, Kedushat HaYom, if you look in your סידור, siddur, your שמונה
עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, what's the ברכה bracha we say? Right? מלך על
כל הארץ, מקדש ישראל...
Melech al kol ha'aretz mekadesh
Yisrael
ויום
הזכרון. v'Yom HaZikaron.
So
and on
שבת Shabbat we add שבת.
Shabbat. Right? So ברוך אתה השם, Baruch Atah Hashem, right? So מלך
על כל הארץ Melech al kol ha'aretz, is מלכויות, Malchuyot, and this
is like normally you just say מקדש השבת, mekadesh HaShabbat, right? And
this is... so this is מלכויות Malchuyot and this is קדושת היום.
Kedushat HaYom. Okay, so we... that's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that's what
we do, but here's interesting thing number one. Once this becomes the
חתימה chatimah for מוסף, Musaf, right? Up first we say all the
מלכויות, Malchuyot, right? How does the מלכויות Malchuyot start? עלינו, Aleinu, right?
עלינו, Aleinu, whatever. Okay, you start the מלכויות Malchuyot and you get
to there. Okay, but once that becomes the חתימה chatimah for the
מלכויות Malchuyot on מוסף, Musaf, this becomes the חתימה chatimah we have
every שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. מלך על
כל הארץ. Melech al kol ha'aretz Doesn't make sense. Every חתימה chatimah
we have in the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei says ברוך אתה השם
מקדש ישראל ויום הזכרון. Baruch Atah Hashem mekadesh Yisrael v'Yom HaZikaron. Like
we say by every other שבת Shabbat and יום טוב, Yom Tov,
but no, this becomes part of the חתימה chatimah and that gets
taken even in the other שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esreis when we do
not start when it's not the whole פסוקים psukim of מלכויות. Malchuyot.
You took like a four words מלך על כל הארץ.
Melech al kol ha'aretz. Right. Okay, so that is the חתימה chatimah
of קדושת... Kedushat... of מלכויות Malchuyot added to the חתימה chatimah of
קדושת היום. Kedushat HaYom. That is the פסק psak of רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, right, and that is part of the... Even though we
don't blow the שופר Shofar in them, even though we don't blow
the, in the other שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esreis, right, we just keep
the liturgy. Now, I want to make another point though, because it
is not so black and white that we ignore the position of
רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, because how, what happens
in the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei after you do מחיה מתים? Mechayeh
Metim? What's the next thing you say on a ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah or יום כיפור after מחיה מתים? Mechayeh Metim? Where do you
go to? Do you say ברוך אתה ה' מחיה המתים? Baruch ata
Hashem Mechayeh Hametim? Then you say אתה קדוש ושמך קדוש? Ata kadosh
v'shimcha kadosh? No, what do you say? What do you say? ובכן,
Ubchein, yeah, ובכן, Ubchein, ובכן תן פחדך, Ubchein ten pachdecha, right, ובכן
תן פחדך, Ubchein ten pachdecha,
right, ובכן תן כבוד, Ubchein ten kavod, פחדך, pachdecha, כבוד, kavod, right,
ובכן תן פחדך, Ubchein ten pachdecha, right, ובכן תן כבוד,
Ubchein ten kavod, פחדך, pachdecha, כבוד, kavod, right, ובכן צדיקים, Ubchein tzadikim,
right, ובכן צדיקים, Ubchein tzadikim, whatever, I don't have a פרינט print
here, ותמלוך
אתה ה' לבדך.
V'timloch
ata Hashem levadecha.
Now, what is all of this doing, right?
This is talking about looking towards the future, right, ובכן תן פחדך
על כל מעשיך, Ubchein ten pachdecha al kol ma'asecha, על כל מה
שעשית, al kol mah she'asita, וישתחוו כל ברואים לעשות רצונך, v'yishtachavu kol
beruim la'asot retzoncha, ותן כבוד, v'ten kavod, right, ובכן צדיקים, Ubchein tzadikim,
etc., ותמלוך אתה ה' לבדך על כל מעשיך בהר ציון. v'timloch ata
Hashem levadecha al kol ma'asecha b'har tziyon. So this, I believe, again,
I'm not sure but I believe this is
a holdover or a
from a רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri liturgy that
had this leading into the, you know, the ברכה beracha of of
קדושת השם. Kedushat Hashem. Now think for a moment, what is the
ברכה beracha we make even according to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Right.
What's the ברכה beracha we make? The ברכה beracha is ברוך אתה
ה', Baruch ata Hashem,
what's the ברכה? beracha?
המלך הקדוש. HaMelech HaKadosh. So we already have המלך הקדוש
HaMelech HaKadosh here, right, we've already have a חתימה chatimah here that
works as a מלכויות Malchuyot חתימה, chatimah, and we have actually a,
right, we have actually a liturgy that precedes it that might well
have
been the a part of a מלכויות Malchuyot type of a liturgy.
Right, the fact that in the end what we do have is,
right, exactly. So we have רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri makes this מלכויות Malchuyot and the חתימה chatimah works, and we
keep that חתימה chatimah for everything, and we kept this, we don't
have the פסוקים, pesukim, so it doesn't really remain the מלכויות, Malchuyot,
but we definitely have that theme, and then we have the מלכויות
Malchuyot here and we have that theme, and the מלך על כל
הארץ Melech al kol ha'aretz. also gets retained in the other שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esreis as well. Okay, so it is you really wind
up having both רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri and
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even though we wind up really fully פוסק
posking like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the מלכויות Malchuyot occur here, but
with the impact that these חתימות, chatimot, right, get preserved, you know,
in the other שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esreis.
Yes, that's a phenomenon in חז"ל's Chazal's מחלוקת, machloket, liturgical מחלוקות. machlokot.
You have them both. מודים, Modim, right. So it's that's beautifully reflective
of that exact predisposition.
Exactly. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
said to him, אם אינו תוקע למלכויות למה הוא מזכיר? Im eino
tokeia l'malchuyot lama hu mazkir? If you're not going to do תקיעות
tekiyot for מלכויות, Malchuyot, why bother saying them at all? So as
I said, that reflects a clear understanding of the tight relationship of
מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofarot to the תקיעות. tekiyot. Either either
one is is helping the other, it could go either way, but
still there's a tight relationship. So the גמרא Gemara says, למה הוא
מזכיר, Lama hu mazkir, why are you mentioning it? רחמנא אמר, Rachmana
amarei, because the תורה Torah says say מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. Malchuyot, Zichronot,
v'Shofarot. We're going to link it to פסוקים pesukim later on. Whether
it really believed it was biblical or not we'll discuss, but either
way, it's there's an obligation to say it. So the גמרא Gemara
does not buy into what seems to be the powerful point of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that these are intimately connected to the תקיעות.
tekiyot. The גמרא Gemara understands that they could exist as an independent
liturgy, so it questions רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's argument that what's the
point of doing it without the תקיעות? tekiyot? So אלא למה עשר
רמיא תשע. Ela lama aser reima tisha. So the גמרא Gemara completely
takes the punch out of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's statement. No, what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva meant to say is, if you're not going
to have the תקיעות tekiyot go with it, you shouldn't say a
full ten פסוקים. pesukim. We'll see in a minute you'll say ten
פסוקים. pesukim. אלא תשע, Ela tisha, you should say nine
פסוקים. pesukim. שינוי, Shinui, you should do something else to indicate they're
different. So it becomes a very weak argument. Yeah, if you're not
doing the תקיעות, tekiyot, why are you doing the full complement of
פסוקים? pesukim? The real point of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, as I
said, is much more powerful, is the idea that these are intimately
interconnected, which also raises, you know, the interesting question of what are
these different positions about. Number one, right, why would it be that
you sort of understand even though מלך על כל הארץ... Melech al
kol ha'aretz That really has so much to do with מקדש ישראל,
mekadesh Yisrael... at least on the face of it, you understand that
you want these to be like in the middle. Right, what is
the idea of רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabi Yochanan Ben Nuri, number
one, if he detaches the תקיעות tkiyos from the מלכויות, malchuyos, and
he pushes this up here, so האל הקדוש, ha-el ha-kadosh, המלך הקדוש,
ha-melech ha-kadosh, you sort of get it, but what's the idea of
sort of pushing the מלך melech in the background and removing it
from the תקיעה tkiya and removing it from the center and just
incorporating it earlier? And I think that one of the ways of
understanding this is, you know, a little bit of the question of
how we understand the theme of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. How much
is the theme of ראש השנה Rosh Hashana to waste the question
of is it like היום הרת עולם, hayom haras olam, the day
of creation? Do we think of it more in terms of the
יום הדין? yom hadin? You know, how much is it a day
of, you know, sort of of announcing God as king, embracing God,
מלך על כל הארץ, Melech al kol ha'aretz... you know, you could
sort of see that as the עיקר, ikar, and the fact that
God remembers the creations, זכרונות, zichronos, and whatever, is sort of is
less central than the idea of a יום של מלכות. yom shel
malchus. And you can even see שופרות shofros as being about מלכות,
malchus, right? לפעמים תריעו לפני המלך השם, lifamim tario lifnei hamelech Hashem,
right? So you could sort of emphasize that, or you could emphasize
what I think most happens in אשכנזי Ashkenazi and ליטבק Litvak shuls,
is the emphasis of a יום הדין, yom hadin, and the idea
of מלכות malchus is like because it's מלכות, malchus, that gets us
to because it's the day of creation, that gets us to the
עיקר ikar of the day which is the fact that we're being
judged, like but that's like the necessary background to explain why this
is a יום הדין. yom hadin. So I wonder if, you know,
to some degree that might be this debate, that by pushing המלך
הקדוש ha-melech ha-kadosh up here, it's really decentralizing it from the theme,
and the real focus of the day, and you're not even having
the תקיעות tkiyos by it, and the real focus of the day
is זכרונות ושופרות, zichronos veshofros, it's all about a יום הדין, yom
hadin, right? And the שופרות shofros connect to that, whereas according to
רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, that you have them all in the middle,
I think you allow sort of like an equal, you know, voice
for any one of those themes. And if you wanted to sort
of מלכויות malchuyos to be seen as a more dominant theme than
perhaps זכרונות. zichronos. So I think it is important again why he
would want to push it earlier and make it like not in
the center and also make it not get the תקיעה. tkiya. So
that's רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabi Yochanan Ben Nuri as opposed to
רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. That's just obviously speculation. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: מניין
שאומרים אבות? minayin sheomrim avos?
How do you know there's an idea, now we're going to look
at the general structure of שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei and then tie
it into ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. How do you know you start
with mentioning the אבות? avos? שנאמר הבו להשם בני אלים. shenemar havu
lashem bnei eilim. Give to God, you know, the sons of rams,
so rams, the strong ones, are considered to be the אבות. avos.
מניין שאומרים גבורות, minayin sheomrim gvuros, the power of God, the might
of God? שנאמר הבו להשם כבוד ועוז, shenemar havu lashem kavod vaoz,
honor and
strength. ומניין שאומרים קדושות, uminayin sheomrim kdushos, that you say like האל
הקדוש ha-el ha-kadosh or המלך הקדוש? ha-melech ha-kadosh? שנאמר
הבו להשם כבוד שמו השתחוו להשם בהדרת קודש, shenemar havu lashem kvod
shmo hishtachavu lashem behadras kodesh, in the glory of the of the
of the sanctity, yes, of the sanctuary.
Yeah, that has nothing to do with ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashana. No, general.
This is just the context structure of the עמידה. Amida. Exactly, the
general structure of שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. Okay. ומניין, uminayin, now we
get to this, so that's the general שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. ומניין
שאומרים מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות? uminayin sheomrim malchuyos zichronos veshofros?
How do you know
that these are themes of ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and are reflected
in the liturgy? רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbi Eliezer omer, דכתיב, dechshiv, the
verse says:
שבתון זכרון תרועה, shabbaton zichron truah, a day of rest, a remembrance
of blast, מקרא קודש, mikra kodesh, a holy day. שבתון, shabbaton, זה
קדושת היום. zeh kdushas hayom. So שבתון shabbaton is you say, you
mention קדושת היום. kdushas hayom. This is read to understand since it's
describing the day, presumably therefore it's going to be reflected in the
liturgy to describe the day. So that is קדושת היום. kdushas hayom.
זכרון, zichron, אלו זכרונות. eilu zichronos. So זכרון, zichron, right, so you
have קדושת היום kdushas hayom and זכרונות. zichronos. תרועה, truah, אלו שופרות.
eilu shofros. Notice what we're missing. We're missing מלכויות, malchuyos, which again
reflects a רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabi Yochanan Ben Nuri, that the
center ones are קדושת היום, kdushas hayom, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות. shofros.
מלכויות malchuyos we're bracketing for now. Okay.
אלו שופרות. eilu shofros. מקרא קודש, mikra kodesh, now what's the last
מקרא קודש? mikra kodesh? קדשהו בעשיית מלאכה. kadsheihu beasiyas melacha. That's no
longer about the liturgy, that just means don't do מלאכה. melacha. Okay,
but we don't have מלכויות. malchuyos. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo
Rebbi Akiva, Rebbi Akiva says to him: מפני מה לא נאמר שבתון
שבות שבו פתח הכתוב תחילה? mipnei ma lo ne'emar shabbaton shvus shebo
patach hakatuv techila? Rebbi Akiva does not seem to be arguing substantively,
but he just says, why did you put the idea of not
doing מלאכה melacha at the end? You should have started by saying
that the word שבתון shabbaton means don't do מלאכה. melacha. That's a
central idea, you know, and then we'll move on to the issues
of the liturgy and what it reflects in terms of other qualities
of the day. So you should have first said it was don't
do מלאכה. melacha. אלא שבתון, ela shabbaton, here's how I would read
the verse says Rebbi Akiva: קדשהו בעשיית מלאכה, kadsheihu beasiyas melacha, don't
do מלאכה. melacha. זכרון, zichron, אלו זכרונות. eilu zichronos. תרועה, truah, אלו
שופרות. eilu shofros. מקרא קודש, mikra kodesh, זו קדושת היום. zu kdushas
hayom. So same thing except that he puts קדושת היום kdushas hayom
at the end, which is not normally what Rebbi Akiva does in
the liturgy, right? Rebbi Akiva admits that the קדושת היום kdushas hayom
comes early. So it's a little bit funny what the whole debate
is about. But anyway, but you get the זכרונות zichronos and שופרות.
shofros. out from זכרון תרועה. zichron teruah. Now מניין שאומרים מלכויות? minayin
she'omrim malchuyos? But where does מלכויות malchuyos come in?
תניא, Tanya, תנא ברייתא, tana beraisa, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, אני ה'
אלוהיכם ובחודש השביעי זו מלכויות. Ani Hashem Elokeichem u’vachodesh hashvii zu malchuyos.
Okay, so the פסוק pasuk says, the פסוק pasuk right before which
talks about לעני ולגר תעזוב אותם, la'ani vela'ger ta'azov osam, אני ה'
אלוהיכם, Ani Hashem Elokeichem, that's talking about leaving the gifts on שבועות.
Shavuos. And then it says ובחודש השביעי, u’vachodesh hashvii, מקרא קודש יהיה
לכם mikra kodesh yihyeh lachem or שבתון זכרון תרועה מקרא קודש, shabbaton
zichron teruah mikra kodesh, כל מלאכת עבודה לא תעשו. kol meleches avodah
lo sa'asu. So it ties in the אני ה' אלוהיכם Ani Hashem
Elokeichem which is understood as מלכות malchus together with ובחודש השביעי u’vachodesh
hashvii זו מלכויות. zu malchuyos. Thank you. So by the way, again,
notice this is a perfect רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rebbi Yochanan ben
Nuri because it is אני ה' אלוהיכם ובחודש
השביעי
Ani Hashem Elokeichem
u’vachodesh hashvii
and שבתון זכרון תרועה.
shabbaton zichron
teruah. So how does this work? It works אני ה' אלוהיכם Ani
Hashem Elokeichem מלכויות, malchuyos, right, קדושת היום, kedushas hayom, I'm sorry, not
קדושת
היום, kedushas hayom, not this,
this is sort of like מלכויות malchuyos here, קדושת היום, kedushas hayom,
שבתון, shabbaton,
זכרונות zichronos and שופרות. shofros. So that is רבי יוחנן בן נורי.
Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri. You put the מלכויות malchuyos with קדושת השם,
kedushas Hashem, אני ה' אלוהיכם ובחודש השביעי. Ani Hashem Elokeichem u’vachodesh hashvii.
Then we get to
שבתון זכרון תרועה, shabbaton zichron teruah, קדושת היום, kedushas hayom, זכרונות, zichronos,
and and שופרות. shofros. The מלכויות malchuyos are like in the background.
They're like before we get to the stuff. אני ה' אלוהיכם ובחודש
השביעי, Ani Hashem Elokeichem u’vachodesh hashvii, but it's prior to the central
characterization of the day. So these פסוקים pesukim work very well with
רבי יוחנן בן נורי דרשה. Rebbi Yochanan ben Nuri drasha. You learn
everything out and you get exactly that order of putting the מלכויות
malchuyos earlier, moving them off of center stage. Okay, so that is
the דרשה. drasha. אני ה' אלוהיכם Ani Hashem Elokeichem ובחודש השביעי u’vachodesh
hashvii זו מלכויות. zu malchuyos. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yosi
berebi Yehuda omer, אינו צריך. eino tzarich. You don't need it from
there. הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, you don't need it from
there, behold the פסוק pasuk says והיו לכם לזכרון לפני אלוהיכם. vehayu
lachem le'zicharon lifnei Elokeichem. Right, this is about the
חצוצרות, chatzotzros, עשה לך שתי חצוצרות כסף, aseh lecha shtei chatzotzros kesef,
which is blasting and it says and they will be for you
זכרון לפני ה' אלוהיכם אני ה' אלוהיכם. zicharon lifnei Hashem Elokeichem Ani
Hashem Elokeichem. So והיו לכם לזכרון vehayu lachem le'zicharon is זכרונות, zichronos,
and לפני ה' אלוהיכם שאין תלמוד לומר אני ה' אלוהיכם, lifnei Hashem
Elokeichem she'ein talmud lomar Ani Hashem Elokeichem, מה תלמוד לומר אני ה'
אלוהיכם, mah talmud lomar Ani Hashem Elokeichem, why does it repeat that?
זהו בנין אב, zehu binyan av, this is a paradigm, לכל מקום
שנאמר בו זכרונות lechol makom shenemar bo zichronos יהיו מלכויות עמהן, yihyu
malchuyos imahen, then the מלכויות malchuyos get tied in with the זכרונות.
zichronos. Now that is a רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva approach. Because this
approach, שבתון זכרון תרועה, shabbaton zichron teruah, there's no idea of מלכויות
malchuyos in the basic characterization, whereas and also the idea of
תקיעות, tekios, if you say that there's an idea of תקיעה, tekiah,
where does the idea of תקיעה tekiah relate to? תרועה. teruah. It
relates to these things. תקיעה tekiah does not relate to the מלכויות.
malchuyos. So this דרשה drasha is a רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rebbi
Yochanan ben Nuri, where according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, if he
learns it from the פסוק pasuk of the
חצוצרות, chatzotzros, the פסוק pasuk of the חצוצרות chatzotzros as where רש"י,
Rashi, by the way, על התורה al ha-Torah emphasizes the דרשה drasha
of מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. malchuyos zichronos ve'shofros. The פסוקים pesukim of the
שופרות shofros say
וביום שמחתכם ובמועדיכם, u'veyom simchaschem u've'moadeichem,
where am I? Okay, ותקעתם בחצוצרות על עולותיכם ועל זבחי שלמיכם והיו
לכם לזכרון לפני אלוהיכם. u’tekatem b’chatzotzros al olosaychem v'al zivchei shalmaychem vehayu
lachem le'zicharon lifnei Elokeichem.
So ותקעתם בחצוצרות u’tekatem b’chatzotzros is שופרות, shofros, obviously ותקעתם. u’tekatem. והיו
לכם לזכרון vehayu lachem le'zicharon is זכרונות. zichronos. אני ה' אלוהיכם Ani
Hashem Elokeichem is מלכויות. malchuyos.
So there, not only are they all taken together as opposed to
here where this is pushed early, they're all wrapped together, but they're
all wrapped together with תקיעות, tekios, with it being about תקיעה. tekiah.
So that's a רבי עקיבא דרשה Rebbi Akiva drasha that learns מלכויות
זכרונות ושופרות malchuyos zichronos ve'shofros as coming all together and תקיעה tekiah
being associated, as opposed to this דרשה, drasha, right, where מלכויות malchuyos
is pushed earlier and the actual תקיעות tekios are not on the
מלכויות, malchuyos, yes?
even though it's חצוצרות. chatzotzros.
חצוצרות, chatzotzros, right, so
you have to loosely associate. Okay, blasts, right, same themes though, exactly.
Okay, so זה בנין אב. zeh binyan av. Okay, so רבי אומר,
Rebbi omer, רבי, תניא, tanya, we're talking about a ברייתא. והיכן אומר
לקדושת היום? ve-heichan omer li'kdushas hayom? Now where are you going to
say the
קדושת היום? kedushas hayom? Where are you going to say the מקדש
ישראל ויום הזכרון? mekadesh Yisrael ve-yom ha-zicharon? Like in our
ברייתא, in our משנה it would have phrased it as where are
you going to do the
מלכויות malchuyos with קדושת היום kedushas hayom with קדושת השם. kedushas Hashem.
But here it's asking where you're going to do קדושת היום. kedushas
hayom. תניא, Tanya, תנא ברייתא, tana beraisa, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, עם
המלכויות אומרה. im ha-malchuyos omrah. You say it together with מלכויות malchuyos
which is what we do, that's the רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva approach.
מה מצינו בכל מקום ברביעית? mah matzinu be-chol makom bi-revias? Now here's
a logic: normally, right, the day is mentioned in the fourth ברכה,
beracha, אף כאן ברביעית, af kan bi-revias, here too be the fourth
ברכה. beracha. Fine. רבי שמעון... Rebbi Shimon... מלכויות malchuyos *Malchiot*, which comes
right after המלך הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh. *HaMelech Hakadosh*, fourth ברכה bracha *Bracha*.
Right comes right after מלכויות malchuyos, *Malchiot*, after המלך הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh,
*HaMelech Hakadosh*. רבי שמעון בן גמליאל אומר omer, *Rebbi Shimon Ben Gamliel
Omer*, עם זכרונות zichronos. אמרה *Im Zichronot Amra*.
So here's a new idea, you say קדושת היום kedushas hayom *Kedushat
Hayom* with the זכרונות zichronos *Zichronot*.
Why? מה מצינו בכל מקום באמצע אף כאן באמצע *Ma matzinu bechol
makom ba’emtza af kan ba’emtza*. You do it in the middle.
So here's a new idea, right?
So the new idea here is that as opposed to here where
you say the, you push מלכויות malchuyos *Malchiot* up, we're assuming like
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rebbi Akiva*, מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות malchuyos, zichronos, and
shofros *Malchiot Zichronot veShofrot* are the center stage, like they are the
story of the day. They're going to come in the middle and
the only question is do you put this with מלכויות malchuyos *Malchiot*
because it's normally right after המלך הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh *HaMelech Hakadosh*, it's
number four, or do you move it down with זכרונות Zichronos *Zichronot*
because it's normally in the middle? Okay, in a way you could
say like what emphasizes the theme that this is of קדושת היום
kedushas hayom, *Kedushat Hayom*, is it the first thing you mention or
is it the fact that it's in the center? But this looks
at it differently. We've already discarded רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri. *Rebbi Yochanan Ben Nuri*, we are looking at this as
the center of the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei, *Shemoneh Esrei*, and the
only point is where do we link the idea of קדושת היום
kedushas hayom, *Kedushat Hayom*? Now I should say by the way, besides
the question of the way it's being framed is, okay, but how
do we give it its right status? Its right status as first
or its right status as at the middle? But the other important
question also is what do we wind up implicitly saying is a
central theme of the day? Right? If you say, right, in מקדש
ישראל mkadesh Yisroel, והזמנים וביום הזכרון *Mekadesh Yisrael veHaZmanim u’veYom HaZichron*, you're
saying מלכויות malchuyos; *Malchiot* and you're saying המלך הקדוש *HaMelech Hakadosh*, המלך
על כל הארץ *HaMelech al kol ha’aretz*, but you're actually saying מלכויות
malchuyos *Malchiot* with מקדש ישראל והזמנים *Mekadesh Yisrael veHaZmanim*, you're making a
pretty clear statement that that is like a, the, a, if not
the center theme of the day. The day of יום הזכרון Yom
HaZikaron *Yom HaZichron* is like מלך כל הארץ *Melech kol ha’aretz* is
מלכויות malchuyos *Malchiot*, right? Whereas as opposed to if you say it
with זכרונות Zichronos *Zichronot*, then it's saying a different thing. Central to
the theme of the day is the זכרונות zichronos *Zichronot*. I do
see this again as this ongoing tension with what is ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah* about? Is it about a יום הדין Yom
HaDin *Yom HaDin* or is it about a יום של מלכות malchus
*Yom shel Malchut*? So where you say the ברכה *Bracha* of מקדש
ישראל *Mekadesh Yisrael*, right, could very well, you know, have an important
message in terms of which theme is central. The other thing that
should be mentioned is the נוסח *Nusach* is מקדש ישראל ויום הזכרון
mekadesh Yisrael v'Yom HaZikaron. *Mekadesh Yisrael veYom HaZichron*. Right, now that's not
so surprising because obviously the רגלים *Regalim* always go together and there
we don't say specifically, we say הזמנים *HaZmanim*, right? Whereas on יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur* we say ויום הכיפורים *veYom HaKippurim*. So the fact
that we're naming it, but still we're naming it יום הזכרון *Yom
HaZichron*, you know, for all you know, for all you know, we
could have named it as יום תרועה *Yom Teruah*, right? We're naming
it יום הזכרון *Yom HaZichron*. So the יום הזכרון *Yom HaZichron*, right,
of the קדושת היום *Kedushat Hayom*, right, brings together in a way
the מלכויות malchuyos. *Malchiot* with the זכרונות zichronot, *Zichronot*. So the question
where you say the קדושת היום *Kedushat Hayom*, if you were to
set it in זכרונות zichronot, *Zichronot*, it would have underscored the central
theme that זכרונות zichronot, *Zichronot* is a central theme. We say it
in מלכויות malchuyos *Malchiot*, which could have made מלכויות Malchuyos *Malchiot* the
entire central theme, but then we say ויום הזכרון *veYom HaZichron*. So
we've got this thing all of מלכויות *Malchiot* but then we label
it as יום הזכרון *Yom HaZichron*. So again, we're sort of keeping
the various themes, continuing to keep them alive. Yes.
Could it just simply be that רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* tradition is
that קדושת היום *Kedushat Hayom* always comes in the center?
Yes, I think that is what he's saying, באמצע *ba’emtza*. Right.
But, but in other words, just structurally. Yes.
Not, not the באמצע *emtza* middle of these, the באמצע *emtza* middle
of the whole שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei. *Shemoneh Esrei*. Yes, yes, I,
he does say that.
Just on שבת *Shabbat* it comes in the center.
Yes, exactly. That's exactly the point.
So why, why why if you
want to, you have to put it right physically in the center.
So I agree, the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is framing it
is just a question of where does it come, like right after
the first three or middle. But I just think that once you
place it in a certain place, it sends a certain message.
Right, and the fact that you move it away from the center,
where do you shift the emphasis?
Oh, I see. Right, the קדושה *Kedusha* on, I see.
Right, it's sort of, you're not, right,
you're not, you're just saying, look, we're just doing the standard thing,
you know, don't draw any conclusions. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
says, let's take a look. וכשקידשו בית דין את ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah באושא *U’chshe’kidshu Beis Din es Rosh Hashanah be’Usha*, when they sanctified
the year in אושא Usha *Usha*, it's a funny way of describing
it. You act as ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah* and you
sanctify the year, but you know, it just, the speak about when
it was ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah* once in אושא *Usha*,
again, never getting away from the theme of קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh
*Kiddush HaChodesh*. So ירד רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא לפני רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *yarad Rebbi Yochanan Ben Beroka lifnei Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel*, רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא *Rebbi Yochanan Ben Beroka* went down in front of
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel*. ועשה כרבי יוחנן בן
נורי *ve’asa ke’Rebbi Yochanan Ben Nuri*. And he acted like רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. *Rebbi Yochanan Ben Nuri*. So forgetting
this debate of, you know, middle or whatever, he put המלך הקדוש
*HaMelech Hakadosh* way up here. Right? So אמר לו רבן שמעון *amar
lo Rabban Shimon*, so רבן שמעון *Rabban Shimon* said, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel* meaning, לא היו נוהגין כן ביבנה *lo
hayu nohagin ken be’Yavneh*. You know, when we were back in יבנה
*Yavneh*, they never did it that way. So ביום שני
*be’Yom Sheni*, now the second day, which is funny. ביום שני *be’Yom
Sheni*? This is the place that they did קידוש החודש *Kiddush HaChodesh*.
There isn't two days of יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So it'll mean
on a, on a later year, but it's not what it sounds
like. It's very strange. Anyway, on the second day, ירד רבי חנינא
בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי *yarad Rebbi Chanina beno shel Rebbi Yose
HaGlili* ועשה כרבי עקיבא *ve’asa ke’Rebbi Akiva*. He did like רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva. *Rebbi Akiva*, which was to put, you know, מלכויות *Malchiot*
in the middle, you know, מלכויות זכרונות zichronot ושופרות *Malchiot Zichronot veShofrot*
in the middle. שופרות Shofaros after המלך הקדוש. אמר רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said, "Ah כך היו נוהגין ביבנה."
kach hayu nohagin b'Yavneh. That's what they used to do. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, so by the way you also see another
important theme, which is these are not just hypothetical debates. You know,
Dov said before the point, which is when there are different debates
do they both get preserved? But one also imagines these debates in
liturgy also started by different practices. You know, there were different traditions
and then the Rabbis were trying to decide which one to make
authoritative, but it's not like other traditions just disappeared. And often like
in the Cairo גניזה Geniza and other places, we find some, you
know, alternate traditions in general to different aspects of liturgy that are
discussed in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so here you have both aspects
of the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. and רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri Okay, למימר, l'meimar, the גמרא Gemara says, דרבי שמעון
בן גמליאל כרבי עקיבא סבירא ליה? d'Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel k'Rabbi Akiva
seira leh? It sounds like he holds like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva,
So והאמר רבי עקיבא מלכויות עם קדושת היום, v'ha amar Rabbi Akiva
malchuyos im kedushas hayom, so but we know in another way he
doesn't hold like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva Maybe he holds like רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva I'm already giving it away a little bit, that
מלכויות זכרונות zichronot ושופרות in the middle. But he debates רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva. where you say, you know, מקדש ישראל ויום הזכרון. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. says you say it number four and he says
you say it number five smack in the middle. So אמר להו
amar lehu אמר רבי עקיבא מלכויות עם קדושת היום אמר להו, amar
Rabbi Akiva malchuyos im kedushas hayom amar lehu, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אמר קדושת היום עם הזכרונות אמר להו. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel amar
kedushas hayom im hazichronos amar lehu. You say קדושת היום with the
זכרונות. zichronot. So he doesn't fully פוסק pasken like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva So אמר רבי זירא לא לומר שתוקעין למלכויות. amar Rabbi Zeira
lo lomar shetokin l'malchuyos. No, no, no, you're right. He's not saying
a straight פסק psak רבי עקיבא. He holds like רבי עקיבא that
מלכויות don't get pushed away into המלך הקדוש, they're in the center,
you do תקיעה tekiah with the מלכויות, right? Again, all of that
is against רבי יוחנן בן נורי. We're not discussing now where you
say קדושת היום, we're discussing that מלכויות comes in the middle and
it gets תקיעות. tekiyos. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara unpacks the other
part. ליום שני ירד רבי חנינא. L'yom sheni yarad Rabbi Chanina. מאי
שני? Mai sheni? What does it mean on the second day? אילימא
יום טוב שני Ileima Yom Tov sheni on the second day of
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, which is what it sounds like, למימר דעברוה
לאלול? l'meimar davru leh l'Elul? That sounds like they did a, you
know, a thirty-day month of אלול. Elul. So the גמרא Gemara. imagined
it could have been in אושא that they had two days and
the first day maybe was בספק b'safek because they didn't know and
in the end they made the 31st day ראש השנה Rosh Hashana.
and there would be a way in which even in the place
where you do קידוש החודש you could have two days if it
wound up that the previous month was a thirty-day one. So you
started that day not knowing. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
ואמר רבי חנינא בר כהנא מימות עזרא ואילך לא מצינו אלול מעובר?
v'amar Rabbi Chanina bar Kahana miymos Ezra v'eylach lo matzinu Elul m'ubar?
But we said that that never really happens although you might remember
earlier we actually did say two times when it did happen, but
okay. So we don't buy that that they really made a two-day
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah אמר רב חסדא מאי שני ליום שני לשנה
הבאה. Amar Rav Chisda mai sheni l'yom sheni l'shanah haba'ah. It means
on a different day in a different year. It doesn't mean the
next day of ראש השנה. All right, didn't exactly sound that way
but fine. So here we have this very central debate of, again,
whether מלכויות gets pushed off, pushed earlier and
bracketed and no תקיעה, tekiah, so taken away from central stage. Right?
And again, in these פסוקים pesukim you do not really have the
theme of מלכויות; to the degree you do, it's pushed earlier. Or
whether מלכויות is central which you get from the פסוקים pesukim of,
you know, of the חצוצרות chatzotzros and therefore it's in the center
and it gets תקיעות. tekiyos. A related question is קדושת היום, does
it come fourth or middle? That could just be a technical question
of what is its right place, but also it might have an
implication on the theme of which one you're centering on in terms
of the nature of the day. And as I said, the fact
that we do it in the fourth but we say מלך אוהב
Melech Ohev and then we say יום הזכרון brings זכרונות back, you
know, sort of gives it equal weight. And then what we're left
with in terms of our liturgy is that the ברכה of המלך
הקדוש and the ובכן u'vechein's reflects really a whole מלכות Malchus, theme
going on here of רבי יוחנן בן נורי which gets retained. And
the fact that the חתימה chatima is מלך על כל הארץ melech
al kol haaretz, מקדש ישראל is the מלכויות חתימה chatima that gets
retained even in the non-מוסף Musaf שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei even when
you're not saying מלכויות. Okay, so it's a little crash course in
how we get to our שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei And now we
get to the direct discussion of the פסוקים. pesukim. Let's take a
look. אין פוחתין מעשרה מלכויות מעשרה זכרונות מעשרה שופרות. Ein pochin m'asarah
malchuyos, m'asarah zichronos, m'asarah shofros. You have to have ten פסוקים pesukim
of each. רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר אם אמר ג' ג' מכולן
יצא. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer im amar gimel gimel mikulun yatza.
If you say three each it's fine. Okay, we'll see what three
each means, says the גמרא. Gemara הני עשרה מלכויות כנגד מי? Hanei
asarah malchuyos k'neged mi? What do these ten מלכויות represent? So אמר
רבי or אמר רבי לוי כנגד עשרה הלולים שאמר דוד בספר תהלים.
amar Rabbi Levi k'neged asarah hillulim she'amar David b'sefer Tehillim. The ten
הלולים, hillulim, you know, הללו hallelujah's that it says in תהלים. Tehillim.
So גמרא Gemara's says הלולים טובא הוו? hillulim tuva havah? Wait a
minute, there's tons of times it says הללו hallelujah in תהלים. Tehillim.
No, הני דכתיב בהו הללוהו בתקע שופר. hanei dechasiv behu halleluhu b'teka
shofar. If you count the ones in that פרק of תהלים Tehillim
of הללוהו בתקע שופר halleluhu b'teka shofar which is about שופר, shofar,
right, you'll get ten. הללוהו בתקע שופר הללוהו בנבל וכנור הללוהו בתוף
ומחול הללוהו במינים ועוגב הללוהו בצלצלי שמע הללוהו בצלצלי תרועה, halleluhu b'teka
shofar, halleluhu b'nevel v'chinor, halleluhu b'tof umachol, halleluhu b'minim v'ugav, halleluhu b'tziltzelei
shamah, halleluhu b'tziltzelei teruah, right? So you count the הללו, hallelu's, right,
הללוהו halleluhu etc., you will get ten. So that's one idea. of
ten praises. Now, of course that can sort of focus on the
idea of מלכות Malchus, *Malchus*, right, of God as king, you know,
ways of praising God, does that idea of the ten correspond to
זכרונות ושופרות *Zichronos ve-Shofros*? Not exactly. So in the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, right,
הללו בצלצלי תרועה *Hallelu be-tziltzelei teruah*, right, so okay fine. So in
the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* they give a different correspondence to the ten of
זכרונות ושופרות *Zichronos ve-Shofros*. I see the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* quotes it,
hold on. Not
just this generic one of הללו *Hallelu*.
Let's take a look.
There's a ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* downstairs.
No, no, no, we're not going to do that.
No, I'm not seeing it. Okay, I might be misremembering. Okay, let's
keep on going.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this. רבי יוחנן אמר כנגד
עשרה מאמרות שבהן נברא העולם *Rabbi Yochanan amar kenegid asara ma'amaros she-behen
nivra ha-olam*.
So going back to this מלכות *Malchus* theme, מלכות *Malchus* in the
sense of what do you do for a king? So first you
praise a king, but also the sense of God as a מלך
*Melech* today is specifically connected to creation of the world. Oh, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says היינו דויאמר *hainu de-Vayomer*. So what's the
עשרה מאמרות *asara ma'amaros*? Ten times it says ויאמר *Vayomer*. But it
doesn't say ויאמר *Vayomer* at בראשית *Bereishis*. Why? תשעה הוו *tisha havu*.
Because the ויאמר *Vayomer*s in בראשית *Bereishis* are only nine, there aren't
ten. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, בראשית נמי מאמר הוא *Bereishis
nami ma'amar hu*. The word בראשית *Bereishis* is also a divine utterance.
שכתוב בדבר ה' שמים נעשו *She-kasuv bi-dvar Hashem shamayim na'asu*. With the
word of God the heavens were created. So when it says בראשית
ברא אלהים את השמים ואת הארץ *Bereishis bara Elokim es ha-shamayim ve-es
ha-aretz*, there was some utterance that caused the creation of שמים וארץ
*shamayim va-aretz* before the ויאמר *Vayomer*s. So this gets back to the
whole debate of do you read the first פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk* as
leading up to when God was creating, God said יהי אור *Yehi
Or*, or in the beginning God created heaven and earth? And if
you read it that way, then there was an active creation of
heaven and earth which is implied in the word בראשית *Bereishis*, really
implied in the word ברא *bara*. Anyway, but that's somehow seen as
the initial divine utterance. The מהרש"א *Maharsha* goes into great length explaining
why it wouldn't have the word of ויאמר *Vayomer*. That בראשית *Bereishis*
is more יש מאין *yesh me-ayin* as opposed to ויאמר *Vayomer* which
is יש מיש *yesh mi-yesh*. Anyway, these types of differences. What?
בראשית *Bereishis* because it's like saying with רֵאשִׁית *reishis*, the word בראשית
*Bereishis*, God created.
So that's the question. Does it just mean right, so that's a
good question, when it says בראשית נמי מאמר *Bereishis nami ma'amar*, does
it just mean that there was an utterance, it's alluding to the
fact that there was an utterance, or that the word בראשית *Bereishis*
itself was the first word? The first like, right, בראשית *Bereishis*, right,
with, oh I see, בראשית *be-reishis*, right. And that's the רש"י *Rashi*
versus
רמב"ן *Ramban*. Right. Okay. So instead of ויאמר *Vayomer* something else.
Right,
so you mean like it's מוסיף *mosif* on something.
When was the first ויאמר *Vayomer*?
Right, it's adding on something. Right. Okay, good. So it says, okay.
רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר אם אמר שלש שלש מכולן יצא *Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri omer im amar shalosh shalosh mi-kullan yatza*. If you
say three of each you're יוצא yotzei. *yotze*. איבעיא להו היכי קתני
*Ibaiya le-hu heichi katani*. What does he mean? שלש מן התורה שלש
מן הנביאים שלש מן הכתובים *shalosh min ha-Torah shalosh min ha-Nevi'im shalosh
min ha-Kesuvim*? In the end we're going to say that you have,
you know, תורה Torah נביאים Nevi'im וכתובים *Torah Nevi'im ve-Kesuvim* and then
you end with one from תורה Torah *Torah*. So when he says
three of each, does he mean three of תורה Torah, *Torah*, three
of נביאים Nevi'im, *Nevi'im*, three of כתובים Kesuvim *Kesuvim*, דהוו תשעה *de-havu
tisha*, which equals nine? ואיכא בינייהו חדא *ve-ika beinaiyhu chada*, and they're
really just debating nine versus ten. The תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* says
ten, he says no, three תורה Torah *Torah*, three נביאים Nevi'im *Nevi'im*,
three כתובים Kesuvim *Kesuvim*, that's enough. אל תגזים *al tagzim*, nine is
enough. Okay, that's one way. או דילמא *O dilma*, or maybe he's
saying no, אחד מן התורה ואחד מן הנביא ואחד מן הכתוב *echad
min ha-Torah ve-echad min ha-Navi ve-echad min ha-Kasuv*. When he says three
of each, he doesn't mean three תורה Torah *Torah*, three נביאים Nevi'im
*Nevi'im*, three כתובים *Kesuvim*. He means three מלכויות *Malchuyos*, three זכרונות *Zichronos*,
and three שופרות Shofaros *Shofros*, one of each of תורה נביאים וכתובים
*Torah Nevi'im ve-Kesuvim*. דהוו להו תלת *de-havu le-hu tlas*, which is three.
ואיכא בינייהו טובא *ve-ika beinaiyhu tuva*, there's a major debate, three versus
ten. תא שמע *Ta shema*, and here דתניא *de-tanya*, אין פוחתין מעשרה
מלכויות מעשרה זכרונות מעשרה שופרות shofaros *ein pochtin me-asara Malchuyos me-asara Zichronos
me-asara Shofros*. ואם אמר שבע מכולן יצא *ve-im amar sheva mi-kullan yatza*,
כנגד שבעה רקיעים *kenegid shiva reki'im*. So here it says בדיעבד *be-diavad*
you can do seven. Interesting seven, how would that get divided between
תורה נביאים וכתובים *Torah Nevi'im ve-Kesuvim*? Maybe two of each with one
final one. Anyway, ten, but בדיעבד *be-diavad* seven's enough. רבי יוחנן בן
נורי אומר הפוחת לא יפחות משבע *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer ha-poches
lo yifchos mi-sheva*, you shouldn't say less than seven. ואם אמר שלש
מכולן יצא *ve-im amar shalosh mi-kullan yatza*, כנגד תורה נביאים וכתובים *kenegid
Torah Nevi'im ve-Kesuvim*. So you see clearly we're not talking about three
תורה *Torah*, three נביאים *Nevi'im* etc. We're talking about the whole unit.
Don't do less than ten, don't do less than seven, and he
says even up to three you'd still, even as little as three
you'd still be יוצא *yotze*. Okay. ואמרי לה כנגד כהנים לויים וישראלים
*Ve-amri lah kenegid Kohanim Leviyim ve-Yisraelim*. Some say כהנים לויים וישראלים *Kohanim
Leviyim ve-Yisraelim* to include the entire Jewish people. Again, I don't know
what to do with these כנגד *kenegids*. אמר רב הונא אמר שמואל
הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן נורי *Amar Rav Huna amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri*, which is quite fascinating. בדיעבד *be-diavad* if you just
say one פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk* of each you're יוצא *yotze*. We're going
to revisit that later when the גמרא *Gemara* says a strange thing
which is even if you just say בתורתך כתוב לאמר *be-Sorascha kasuv
leimor* you're יוצא *yotze* without even saying any פסוקים psukim *pesukim*. But
for now we're saying we rule like רבי יוחנן בן נורי *Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri* that at least בדיעבד *be-diavad* three is enough. Now
we get to choosing the פסוקים psukim *pesukim*. אין מזכירין *ein mazkirin*
okay, זכרון Zichron, מלכות ושופר *Zichron Malchus ve-Shofar* that's our גרסא *girsa*.
Others have the גרסא *girsa* מלכות זכרון Zichron ושופר *Malchus Zichron ve-Shofar*.
זכרונות ושופרות, okay, to get the order right. Anyway, של פורענות, shel
puranus, you do not say the ones that refer to like, you
know, bad things happening to people.
מתחיל בתורה, Maschil ba'Torah, you start תורה first, ומשלים בנביא, u'mashlim b'Navi,
then you say נביא, Navi, and then you and then you end
with נביא. Navi. So it's תורה כתובים נביאים. Torah Kesuvim Nevi'im. ר'
יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosi omer השלים בתורה יצא, hishlim ba'Torah yatza, you
could end if you're end with תורה you're יוצא. Now we know
we דוקא davka do make the 10th one תורה, so the גמרא
will rephrase that. I want to say just one word on what
this weird order is of תורה כתובים נביאים, Torah Kesuvim Nevi'im, right
normally we do תורה נביאים כתובים. Torah Nevi'im Kesuvim. So some of
the ראשונים Rishonim say, well, we're trying to go up in order
so we do כתובים and נביאים but you really can't have to
start with תורה so that's threw the order off. Anyway, the best
explanation I heard and I'm trying to remember who said it, but
is that it's in order to allow the liturgy to progress from
past, present to future. Because if you think about it, basically the
פסוקים psukim from כתובים are from תהלים, Tehillim, are from דוד המלך.
Dovid HaMelech. And therefore so number one some people want to say
chronologically תהלים Tehillim was written before נביאים, I mean most of the
נביאים we quote from are post דוד המלך. Dovid HaMelech. That's the
chronology of it being written, but in terms of how it functions
liturgically, right in the תפילה, tefillah, right the פסוקים psukim we quote
from the תורה look back, the פסוקים psukim we quote from תהלים
Tehillim talk about praising God, so they talk about our present, what
in our present, right, how the themes of מלכות, זכרונות and שופרות
play out in our present in the present, and the נביאים look
tend to look towards the Messianic future. So it's about how we
are bringing those themes of מלכות, זכרונות and שופרות into our backwards
looking, into our present and towards the future. I think that that's
really the best explanation for that. Okay so now the גמרא going
to discuss these choosing which פסוקים psukim you can and cannot use.
So now we're going to look for פסוקים psukim of פורענויות puranios
of sort of, you know, of bad things that are not supposed
to be used. מלכויות כגון, k'gon, what would be an example of
a bad פסוק, pasuk bad פסוק, pasuk of a פסוק pasuk that
would be inappropriate? חי אני נאם ה' אלקים אם לא ביד חזקה
ובזרוע נטויה ובחמה שפוכה אמלוך עליכם. Chai ani neum Hashem Elokim im
lo b'yad chazaka u'vizroa netuya u'vichema shfucha emloch aleichem. Yeah, that's not
a פסוק pasuk. you want to be saying on ראש השנה, right,
with an outstretched hand and pouring forth wrath I will be I
will king upon you. Okay, ואף על גב דאמר רב נחמן v'af
al gav d'amar Rav Nachman כולי האי לירחקינהו ורצי קודשא בריך הוא
עלן וליפרקינן, kula hai l'irchkinu v'ratzi Kudsha Brich Hu alan v'lifarkinan,
so God should have all this anger on us as long as
eventually He redeems us, let Him get His anger out on us
but ultimately it should lead to a גאולה. geula. Nevertheless, כיון דברתחא
אמור keivan d'v'ritcha amor since it is said in anger and in
heat, וברתחא ברישא דשתא לא מדכרינן, u'v'ritcha b'reisha d'shata lo madchrinan, we
do not want to evoke or to remember, you know, mention that
type of anger that God has on us on ראש השנה. זכרון,
what would be זכרונות of פורענויות? puranios? כגון ויזכור כי בשר המה,
k'gon vayizkor ki basar hema, and God remembers they were flesh, and
that could be a good thing, but the end of the פסוק
pasuk is, wait
the end of the
פסוק. pasuk? You have the end of the פסוק pasuk quoted there?
It's Psalm 78 verse 39.
ויזכור
כי בשר המה רוח הולך ולא ישוב.
Vayizkor ki basar
hema ruach holech v'lo yashuv. כמה ימרוהו במדבר יעציבוהו בישימון וישובו וינסו
אל וקדוש ישראל התוו. Kama yamruhu bamidbar ya'atzivuhu bishimon vayashuvu vaynassu El
u'Kdosh Yisrael hisvu. So later פסוקים make it clear that it's about
obviously about doing bad things. Okay, שופר, shofar, what's a שופר shofar
פורענויות? puranios? כגון תקעו שופר בגבעה, k'gon tiku shofar ba'Giva, blow the
שופר shofar in גבעה Giva and what's the end of the פסוק?
You have it there?
הושע Hoshea chapter 5 verse 8.
Yeah.
I thought some of those גמרות Gemaros have the what do you
call it the full פסוק quoted on the side.
תקעו שופר בגבעה חצוצרה ברמה הריעו בית און אחריך
בנימין.
Tiku shofar ba'Giva chatzotzra ba'Rama hari'u Beis Aven
acharecha Binyamin.
Okay,
well that's not clear what's so bad about that, but presumably we
can assume, I have to admit I did not check.
It's the destruction of בנימין.
Binyamin. Okay, in the context it's not a good thing. All right,
so that would be an example of שופרות of of פורענויות. puranios.
Okay. Now, אבל אם באו לומר מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות של פורענות של
עובדי כוכבים, aval im bau lomar Malchuyos Zichronos u'Shofaros shel puranus shel
ovdei kochavim, now if you want to mention bad things happening to
the non-Jews, אומר, you can. And this is an important question about,
on the one hand it's a day of universal judgment of you
know God king מלך על כל הארץ, melech al kol ha'aretz, and
we're going to mention that in a minute, you have to emphasize
king over the whole world. כל באי עולם עוברים לפניו, Kol ba'ei
olam ovrim lefanav, right
so maybe we should you know hope for the good of the
whole world. How much you know does it become focused as a
Jewish יום הדין Yom HaDin and and so on and is interesting.
So here's it says that you're allowed you can say that.
I mean it's acknowledging that it's the יום הדין Yom Hadin, you
just want bad things to happen
to them. כגון, K'gon, like it says, ה' מלך ירגזו עמים, Hashem
malach yirgezu amim,
the nations will tremble, וכגון u'k'gon and for example ה' מלך עולם
ועד אבדו גוים מארצו, Hashem melech olam va'ed avdu goyim m'artzo,
the nations will be will be driven from His land. זכרון כגון,
k'gon, זכור ה' לבני אדום את יום ירושלים האומרים ערו ערו, Zichor
Hashem livnei Edom es yom Yerushalayim ha'omrim aru aru, right bring the
punishment to the children of אדום Edom that caused the destruction of
the Temple. שופר Shofar כגון, k'gon, וה' אלקים בשופר יתקע והלך בסערות
תימן, v'Hashem Elokim b'shofar yitka v'halach b'sa'aros Teiman, וכתיב ה' צבאות יגן
עליהם. u'ksiv Hashem Tzva'os yagen aleihem.
So God protects the Jewish people, right, and brings this sort of
bad stuff on the non-Jews. So that it says is actually acceptable
and again that's like a little, you know, a little discordance for
those that want to really emphasize the complete sort of positive universalist
theme. אין מזכירין זכרון של יחיד, Ein mazkirin zichron shel yachid,
now you do not mention God remembering individuals. Again that this is
a national יום הדין, we're supposed to be thinking of ourselves, obviously
when you pray, you know, for a lot of people ראש השנה
is very much focused on, you know, you know, yourself, your family,
your own תשובה, teshuva, but here it's emphasizing that no, the, you
know, the, this is really, the themes in the שמונה עשרה like
always the themes in the שמונה עשרה are communal and national. So
you do not mention that of an individual, ואפילו לטובה, v'afillu l'tovah,
even a positive one, כגון זכרני ה' ברצון עמך, kegon zachreini Hashem
birtzon amecha, וכגון זכרה לי אלוקי לטובה. v'chegon zachrah li Elokai l'tovah.
Okay,
now of course we do sort of say by God remembering נח,
Noach, okay, but we're gonna get to that. When individuals are remembered
but it's ultimately a way of remembering the whole world, that's a
little bit different. So let's just read a little bit more about
this. פקדונות הרי הם כזכרונות. Pikdonot harei hem k'zichronot. When it says
God פקד, pakad, that's like זכרונות, כגון וה' פקד את שרה, kegon
v'Hashem pakad et Sarah, וכן פקוד פקדתי אתכם, v'chen pakod pakadeti etchem,
דברי רבי יוסי. Divrei Rabbi Yossi. רבי יהודה אומר אינם כזכרונות. Rabbi
Yehuda omer einam k'zichronot. No, it has to be, it has to
be זכרונות, not פקד. pakad. Now why? So the מהרש"א points out
it's not just a different terminology for the same word, there's a
difference. To be זוכר zocher means to constantly remember. Okay, or to
have sort of ongoing in mind. To be פוקד poked means to
sort of, you know, to remember at a particular time. וה' פקד
את שרה, v'Hashem pakad et Sarah, like it's in the calendar, you
know, that you remember at this time to do something, you know,
to or it's momentary. As opposed to זכרונות, it could be זכרונות
is at a moment, right, when it says that they called out
to God in מצרים, Mitzrayim, what does it say? וישמע אלוקים את
נאקתם ויזכור אלוקים את בריתו. Vayishma Elokim et na'akatam vayizkor Elokim et
brito.
But פקד pakad specifically means he says like to have a fixed
time to remember to do something like at that time, you know,
or, you know, something that was said you're going to do. Whereas
opposed זכרונות is more constant. So you don't say פקד, pakad, you
speak about זכרונות. וכגון, v'chegon,
okay, ולרבי יוסי, v'leRabbi Yossi, let's just read one more line of
the גמרא, ולרבי יוסי נהי נמי דפקדונות הרי הם כזכרונות, v'leRabbi Yossi
nehi nami d'pikdonot harei hem k'zichronot, even if פקד pakad counts, וה'
פקד את שרה פקדון דיחיד הוא, v'Hashem pakad et Sarah pikdon d'yachid
hu, that's an individual's, it's not, it's just שרה. Sarah. So גמרא
says no, כיון דאתו רבים מינה, keivan d'atu rabbim mimena, since all
of the many came from her, you know, a lot of people
many people came from her. Okay, כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael came from
her. כרבים דמיא, K'rabbim damya, it's like the רבים. rabbim. Okay, so
we will pick up from this and continue to look at the
various פסוקים tomorrow.